Good everybody. We pick today's דף Daf is כ"ו Chaf Vav 26,
but we pick up with the גמרא Gemara right after the משנה
Mishnah at the bottom of כ"ה עמוד ב. Chaf He Amud Bet.
I wanted to make one or two interesting points about the remainder
of these משניות. Mishnayot. You know we've been dealing with what's true
for A is not true for B, what's true for B is
not true for A, but this משנה Mishnah that we just read
talking about
water that was soaked in leaves and had some wine juice or
grape juice and is in the process of fermenting is not really
the same. It's not really what's true for A is not true
for B; it's talking about one thing that's sort of in a
process, in a stage, and it says at this stage it's still
water and at a later stage it's wine. So it's slightly different.
רש"י Rashi points that out. Obviously they're somewhat similar, you know, here
these things are true for it and not others and at this
stage other things are true and not the same. But it's not
two different objects or two different spheres; it's one thing undergoing a
process. We're going to see that in some of the later משניות
Mishnayot as well. So that's just one thing to realize that we're
not exactly keeping to the structure. Another thing I wanted to say,
and I was sort of almost saying it jokingly yesterday but then
I checked and it actually works out, is that, you know, we
have been doing like a survey of a lot of different topics
with this structure of what's true for A, not true for B.
And if you think about it what have we covered so far?
We've covered קדשים. Kodashim. We dealt with things
like which type of bird you bring a sacrifice, פרה אדומה, Parah
Adumah, עגלה ערופה, Eglah Arufah, and so on. Then we dealt with,
so there was two things about קדשים, Kodashim, then we dealt with
טהרות, Taharos, you know about wooden vessels, metal vessels, pottery vessels and
so on. Yesterday we dealt with זרעים. Zeraim. We dealt with questions
about the what do you call it the nuts, bitter nuts, not
yet bitter nuts, etc. and our משנה Mishnah as well
about the when is something considered wine is a זרעים Zeraim question,
about when is it obligated in תרומות ומעשרות, Terumos UMa'asros, when you
can you buy it with כסף מעשר—I Kesef Ma'aser mean it also
touches on a מקוה Mikvah question but still זרעים. Zeraim. So that's
three of the סדרים. Sedarim. And now if you look the next
three משניות Mishnayot from here to the end covers the next three
סדרים. Sedarim. So the end of our משנה Mishnah dealt with you
know with brothers that inherit an
estate and basically when is that considered to be like one estate
or two estates—it's true that it did apply that issue
to the question of מעשר בהמה, Ma'asar Behemah, so maybe that's a
little bit of a stretch, although אחים השותפים Achim HaShutafim is a
very sort of common question in civil law, how to conceive of
it. So maybe that's the stretch, but the next משנה Mishnah is
straight משנה Mishnah about נשים. Nashim. It's about a girl, at what
stage do certain things apply to an underage girl and other
things—yeah yeah that's about a girl, it sounds like it's about... we'll
talk about it. And then so there's two things from נשים Nashim
and then the last thing is from מועד. Mo'ed. So I actually
think that this is very intentional that you actually have them covered
separately, they're not mixed together; you actually have
קדשים, Kodashim, טהרות, Taharos, זרעים, Zeraim, נזיקין, Nezikin, נשים, Nashim, מועד, Mo'ed,
each covered through this structure. I admit the נזיקין Nezikin one is
maybe a little bit of a stretch but I still think the
fundamental concept is a נזיקין Nezikin one. I don't think it's by
chance that we happen to be looking at all the ששה סדרי
Shisha Sidrei and that again they're not even mixed together, that each
one is dealt with separately. Let's take a look, with that introduction,
let's take a look at our גמרא Gemara which is dealing with
this water which has some grape juice in it and when is
it considered water and when is it considered wine. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this. So the משנה Mishnah said that it's considered
wine when it ferments. So let's see the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא
Gemara says, can you just tilt that a little bit so it
hits me? Let's see. Okay. מאן מתניתין? Mani Matnitin? Who is our
משנה? Mishnah? לא רבי יהודה ולא רבנן. Lo Rebbe Yehuda Velo Rabbanan.
It's not רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda and it's not the רבנן Rabbanan
that we taught of in a ברייתא. Beraita. It's not... we taught
it in a משנה Mishnah rather; we taught in a משנה Mishnah
in מעשרות: Ma'asros: המתמד ונתן מים במדה. HaMetamed VeNatan Mayim BeMidah. If
somebody is doing this process called מתמד, Metamed, which is the water
in the grape
leaves in order to make it into a type of a weak
wine, and you put water in a certain measure—you know, you put
in ten gallons of water—ומצא כדי מדתו. UMatza Kedei Midato. And now
that you've removed the water, there's also ten gallons. The significance being
that whatever amount of grape juice went into the water it can't
be that significant because you don't have a greater amount of liquid
that you're removing than you put in, so whatever amount of flavor
came from the grapes, it's not significant enough that it really was
detectable through being measured in terms of the quantity, okay? So you
remove the same amount of water that you put in. So is
it considered water or wine? So פטור, Patur, it is exempt from
תרומות ומעשרות. Terumos UMa'asros. It's considered to be water because if there's
clearly no grape juice in here or no measurable grape juice it's
water. רבי יהודה מחייב. Rebbe Yehuda Mechayev. רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda obligates.
He says nope doesn't matter, it's considered to be wine and therefore
חייב Chayav in תרומות ומעשרות. Terumos UMa'asros. So מאן, Mani, who is
our... so notice neither of them talk about whether it has fermented
or not, all they talk about is has there been an increase
in the quantity. not the issue our משנה mishna focused on. They're
asking the same question, is it water or wine, okay, but our
משנה mishna focuses on the question of fermenting, and this focuses on
the question of has there been a greater quantity? Can you measure
that there's more that grape juice is now present? So who is
our משנה? mishna? מני, mani, who's our משנה? mishna? אי רבנן, ei
Rabbanan, if it's the Rabbis, אף על גב דהחמיץ, af al gav
de-hichmit, so that's not true. The Rabbis seem to say that you
know that even if it's you know even if it ferments, they
the Rabbis seem to say it doesn't matter if there's the same
amount that you put in, it's considered to be water. אי רבי
יהודה, ei Rebbi Yehuda, if it's רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, אף על
גב דלא החמיץ. af al gav de-lo hichmit. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda
is the opposite. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda doesn't require it to ferment.
So basically what it's basically pointing out is our משנה mishna has
a completely different way of determining this issue than this debate. Our
משנה mishna determines based on fermenting. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda and the
Rabbis, at least the Rabbis, determine it based on an increase quantity.
So how do you reconcile our משנה's mishna way of measuring from
רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda and the Rabbis' way of measuring?
So tough to understand how you'd get or wouldn't get an increased
quantity.
Well, maybe the amount solid, well okay, either it's very trivial and
it can't be measured, right? I mean, you know, if you think
about, by the way, how much flavoring do they add to food,
you know, but that's of course stuff that's chemically designed to give
an enormous amount of taste for a tiny quantity. But it could
be that it is very small or it's a little bit but
it's not so measurable. You didn't leave it in long enough, you
know, or it could be that there was an exchange that a
certain amount of water got absorbed into the grape skins and whatever
and an equal amount of flavor came out.
Which in case can be a lot,
which in case it could be a lot, but again but maybe
that's the debate. Maybe the Rabbis feel that if it can't be
measured, even if it's possible there is grape flavor in there, if
you can't measure its presence, it's not like it's really there. רבי
יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says not necessarily, okay?
So, but I would say that it should also, and this is
not introduced to you, the concept of time. Like the longer it's
in there, the longer the more of a chance you have to
evaporate, which case anything that was replaced clearly would have been by
flavor as opposed to
if you just did it that day. Okay, could be. Which obviously
raises the question, what שיעור shiur does רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda have?
Because if רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda just says yes it is considered
wine, what, automatically? So we'll see about that. So let's take a
look. Okay, so אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה, amar Rav
Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha, so top of כ"ו עמוד א', chaf
vav amud aleph, so here's the first way of reconciling these two
different ways of measuring.
בשהחמיץ מחלוקת. beshe-hichmit machloket. No, the whole debate, and this helps us
understand רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda and the Rabbis,
is that the this water wine, whatever, has fermented. So it has
fermented, so there's a good reason to call it wine. And that's
why רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda calls it wine. It's only that the
Rabbis say, it's very nice that it fermented, but if you can't
measure the presence of any grape juice in it, so okay, you've
effected fermentation, but I'm not ready to call it wine if you
can't actually measure the presence of grape juice. So that's the debate.
When it's fermented.
You mean because it hasn't changed color or something? Like how would
you know the presence...
No, because you took out more than liquid than you put in.
Oh, that'd be the only way.
That's how they determine you measure it. But it has fermented.
Regardless of evaporation.
Presumably. I mean, I don't know, but that's what they seem to
be saying. What?
It's covered, there's no evaporation.
Right. So anyway, okay, so that's what we're talking about, that it
has fermented, and therefore you understand רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, he doesn't
care about quantity, but now that we're talking about it has fermented,
ומתניתין u-matnisen רבי יהודה. Rebbi Yehuda. So our משנה mishna that says
that the only criterion is fermentation is רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, because
רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda notices not adding a criterion, the Rabbis add
a criterion, it has to be more than you put in. רבי
יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says, I don't need that. So basically our משנה
mishna is רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, because our משנה mishna does not
talk about a criterion of quantity, and therefore, assuming that the debate
of רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda and the Rabbis is when it is
when it fermented, which makes sense, or else what's the logic of
the Rabbis? So now our משנה mishna is רבי יהודה. Rebbi Yehuda.
רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda cares about fermentation, but he does not care
about about additional quantity.
וכן אמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא, ve-chen amar Rebbi Yose b'Rebbi Chanina,
בשהחמיץ מחלוקת, beshe-hichmit machloket, the debate is when it's fermented, or else
there's no good way of understanding what the Rabbis, if it hasn't...
I mean, of understanding רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, if it hasn't fermented,
how could you say it's considered wine? ואמר רב נחמן אמר רבה
בר אבוה, v'amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha, and we have
a similar statement of רב נחמן Rav Nachman in the name of
רבה בר אבוה, Rabbah bar Avuha, תמד, temed, again this issue, תמד
temed again this, again I don't know if there's an English term
for it, but anyway, this water, this watered wine, what, you know,
wine'd water is really more technically what it is, this water that
has been given, you know, has absorbed some of
these some of this grape juice, שלקחו בכסף מעשר, shelakcho be-kesef ma'aser,
you purchased it with מעשר ma'aser money. Remember, that's what our משנה
mishna said, that if it fermented, it's considered wine and you can
purchase it with מעשר ma'aser money. So you purchased it with מעשר
ma'aser money, but you purchased it before it fermented, ובסוף, u-vesof,
and in the end, החמיץ, hichmit, it fermented, קנה מעשר, kana ma'aser,
so then your מעשר ma'aser money acquired it and meaning the sanctity
of the מעשר ma'aser trans-, you know, transferred to this water wine,
and it was a good purchase with מעשר ma'aser money. So what
he is actually saying is, another way to frame what he is
saying is, our משנה mishna says it has to have fermented. He
is saying, it doesn't even have to have fermented yet. As long
as, if it eventually ferments, then at the at the... we can
retroactively say that this was wine because this was something that was
going to ferment.
Okay, so you bought water and now it's wine, we don't say
that. And then you and
then your מעשר maaser money the sanctity did not transfer. We don't
say that. We say since in the end it fermented, we see
that when you bought it it was going to ferment, so we
see that even at that time it was considered wine. So what
he is basically saying is although our משנה mishna talks about fermenting,
the real key is the ability to ferment, it will ferment in
the future and that will be determined by future events. Okay, so
that is what he says to qualify the statement of the משנה,
mishna, yes. Wait, let me just read the explaining line: קנה מעשר
מאי טעמא? kana maaser mai taama? Why does this work? איגלאי מילתא
למפרע דפירי הוא iglay milta lemafrea depeyra hu because now the issue
has been revealed retroactively
that it is considered to be fruit, meaning a fruit product, it
was considered wine. Since in the end it fermented, we see now
retroactively that it was going to ferment and therefore it was always
considered wine. Now to reconcile it with the משנה. mishna. אלא מתניתין,
ela masnisin, so what do you do with our משנה? mishna? דקתני
החמיץ אין לא החמיץ לא. dektani hichmitz in lo hichmitz lo.
Our משנה mishna focuses on has it actually fermented?
If it has fermented it's good, if it has not fermented it's
not wine. דילמא אי שבקתיה הוה מחמיץ. dilma ishavte havei machmitz. Why
does our משנה mishna say that if it hasn't fermented it's considered
water? Maybe according to you, if you would have left it around,
it would have eventually fermented and you would have figured out it
was wine. So that's true in either law of the משנה. mishna.
Remember our משנה mishna has two laws: if it's water, it invalidates
a מקוה mikvah and it doesn't work to buy it with מעשר
maaser money; if it's wine, you can buy it with מעשר maaser
money and it does not invalidate a מקוה. mikvah. So it says
how can you make any determination in our משנה, mishna, you make
a ruling based on right now has it fermented? According to what
you said, רבה בר אבוה, Rabba bar Avuha, how are you able
to make a ruling based on whether it's fermented right now? You
should have to wait, see whether it will ferment, and then you'll
be able to make a ruling to determine what its status is.
Okay, which is a very good question. Meaning our משנה mishna talks
about has it already fermented and you're changing the criterion, you're saying
the issue is will it ferment or not? So how do you
deal with the משנה? mishna? Maybe if you would have left it
around according to you it would have fermented in the future. So
אמר רבה, amar Rabba, so רבה Rabba says: כששייר ממנו בכוס ולא
החמיץ. kesheshayer mimenu bekos velo hichmitz.
So רבה Rabba says you know what, you're right. Our משנה mishna
according to this approach, that it's about fermenting in the future, should
not be read to say that we only look at it at
this moment. Our משנה mishna is talking that you left over a
little sample. Okay, so this water spilled into a מקוה, mikvah, or
you used your מעשר maaser money for it, and you leave over
a little sample and you're going to check that sample in I
don't know a day or a week or whatever to see if
it ferments. If that sample ferments, then you'll determine it was wine.
If that sample doesn't ferment, you'll determine it was water. So the
basic answer is you're right, the משנה mishna is talking about has
it fermented, but I'm going to choose to read the משנה mishna
not has it fermented now, but has a sample fermented, does it
ferment in the future? Okay, so it's not obviously פשט pshat of
the משנה, mishna, but this is how we reconcile. The משנה mishna
says the criterion is has it fermented at this moment it's wine,
רבה בר אבוה Rabba bar Avuha says it's wine if it will
ferment in the future, if it does ferment in the future. And
he reads that into the משנה mishna by saying when the משנה
mishna says you look if it fermented, it means you look at
a sample that you held over to determine if that sample fermented
in the future. And then that will retroactively tell us whether or
not it was wine at the critical moment. Michael, you have a
question?
So right now, since it was wine or whatever it is, if
it did change whether it did ferment or not, so in that
intervening week, so we're going to say retroactively everyone who was—yes, yes.
Basically what he is saying is if you had a chemical test
you could run right now and which should tell you at this
moment when it fell in the מקוה mikvah or you bought it
with your מעשר maaser money that it will ferment, then you would
know right now that it's wine. The thing is we don't have
a test. We can't put it under the microscope, they didn't have
microscopes. So how do I determine if it's wine or not? How
do I determine if it will ferment? Not by sort of you
know doing a test right now, but by doing a test that
will take a week. But if at the end of the week
I see that it fermented, it told me that a week ago
it was already wine. It already had, it already was going to
ferment and that makes it wine.
But I thought the whole point was whether or not it really
did ferment?
Well, that's exactly what רבה בר אבוה Rabba bar Avuha is saying.
He's saying I don't, meaning I don't agree or I'm reinterpreting the
משנה mishna and what defines it as wine is not that it
did ferment, what defines it as wine is that it has the
potential to ferment. Consider if instead it was grape juice. Now of
course grape juice is also not water, and here it's not so
much about being wine as not being water, but like what would
he say about grape juice, right, that has the potential to ferment
but has not yet fermented. Is it wine or is it grape
juice? Okay, so for example, there's actually an interesting question. I raised
this, we did this, this came up in מנחות. Menachot. The גמרא
Gemara says that if you take day-old grape juice you can use
it for קידוש. kiddush. Okay, so some people want to say from
that
that therefore you can use nowadays grape juice for קידוש. kiddush. The
difference is that in the גמרא Gemara day-old grape juice was going
to become wine if you left it to ferment. The grape juice
we drink has
been what's the word The only reason the גמרא Gemara said day
old juice from the grape is wine is because it will eventually
become wine. Okay, so there you have it. So the issue is,
yes, you can define something right now based on will it ferment,
but it might be that given our limits of running tests, we'll
only know the answer to that based on the future. But he's
saying, I don't agree with the פשט pshat of the משנה. Mishnah.
The פשט pshat of the משנה Mishnah says has it fermented and
I say will it ferment? Okay, that's what he's introducing into the
discourse.
But the whole thing, anyways, this whole thing with regards to the
מקוה, mikvah, wouldn't we when we did this last time, you know,
it depended on whether what color it was and all that?
No, we'll get to color in a minute. Right now the issue
is not color, right now the issue is water. Drawn water invalidates
a מקוה. mikvah. Drawn other liquids does not invalidate a מקוה, mikvah,
even if it's clear. You could take milk, clear milk, thin milk,
or white wine that does not has not a color issue, and
the issue is water invalidates a מקוה, mikvah, drawn water. Whereas drawn
other liquids does not. Okay, so the issue is water or not,
yes.
Is the issue with the future statement be where that is in
process?
In other words, fermentation is begins immediately, and the question is whether
there's a threshold that something is fermented or whether once it's in
process of fermenting you can treat it as if it's fermented.
Right.
So okay, so what you're saying is a way to reframe the
statement is not just something that will ferment is considered wine, but
something in process of fermenting is considered wine. Right, that's that's good.
That's probably a better way to reframe it, which helps explain why
we give it the definition right now. It's not just that it
has the capacity to, but it's actually already in that process. So
that's a very good point. Okay, good. All right, so now that's
so that's his explanation, that that's his approach, and the way to
read it in the משנה Mishnah is to just re-read the משנה.
Mishnah. It's not about has it fermented, but as David has said,
either will it ferment or as David has said, is it in
the process of fermenting? So let's now the גמרא Gemara though does
introduce another approach to this, another way of reconciling it. And this
gets to some of the issues that Michael was was bringing in.
רב אמר הא מני רבי יוחנן בן נורי היא. Rav amar hamani
Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri hi. This is רבי יוחנן בן נורי. Rabbi
Yochanan ben Nuri. דתנן ketnan we taught in the משנה: Mishnah: ג'
לוגין מים חסר קורטוב שנפל לתוכן קורטוב יין. gimmel lugin mayim chaser
kortov shenafal letochan kortov yayin. Now there's a whole big question about
what the גירסא girsa is here. We're going to read the gir,
actually it's not a question that the ראשונים Rishonim raise, the גמרא
Gemara in מכות Makkos has a whole question what the right גירסא
girsa of this משנה Mishnah is. We're going to read it as
it's printed in front of us. Okay, so ג' לוגין מים. gimmel
lugin mayim. Now the amount of drawn water, by drawn, you know,
I mean not like rainwater, stuff that you draw with a bucket
or run through a pipe or something like that. The amount of
drawn water that invalidates a מקוה, mikvah, if the מקוה mikvah does
not yet have 40 סאה. se'ah. Again, once the מקוה mikvah has
40 סאה, se'ah, you can add drawn water, that's what we do
every day to our מקואות. mikvahs. But if it doesn't have 40
סאה, se'ah, drawn water invalidates. The amount is three לוג. log. How
much is a לוג? log? A לוג log is about 12 to
14 ounces. So three לוג log is what, 36, 12, 42 ounces.
So what is that? What's a liter? A liter is
33 ounces about. Okay, so you think about a liter bottle of
soda, so it's about what is it, about like a liter and
a third. Okay, so that amount of drawn water invalidates a מקוה.
mikvah. Okay, now let's say it's missing a קורטוב. kortov. A קורטוב
kortov is like a tiny amount, a gram. Okay, so it doesn't
matter, you need the full amount, anything less than the full amount
does not invalidate. That's the law with שיעורים, shiurim, you need the
full amount. So ג' לוגין מים, gimmel lugin mayim, three לוג, log,
חסר קורטוב, chaser kortov, that's missing like a thimble worth, שנפל לתוכן,
shenafal letochan, now so it can't invalidate a מקוה. mikvah. What happened?
שנפל לתוכן קורטוב יין. shenafal letochan kortov yayin.
Wine fell in, a little bit of wine. ומראיהן כמראה יין, umarean
kemarei yayin, it looks like wine. Now there's two reasons to say
that this now mixture is not a problem. Number one, it only
it does not have three לוג log of water. It has 2.99
לוג log of water and 0.01 לוג log of wine. So it
doesn't even have three לוג log of water. And it doesn't even
look like water, it looks like wine. So there's two reasons to
say it's not a problem and that's what the משנה Mishnah says:
לא פסול, lo pasul, did not invalidate. Okay, that was the easy
case. Now we go on to another case. ג' לוגין מים חסר
קורטוב, gimmel lugin mayim chaser kortov, the same 2.99 לוגין lugin of
water, שנפל לתוכן קורטוב חלב, shenafal letochan kortov chalav, which 0.01 amount
of milk fell in. So now what do you have? ומראיהן כמראה
מים, umarean kemarei mayim, and it looks like water. So now what
do you have? You have in actuality you only you don't have
three לוג log of water, you only have 2.99 לוג log of
water, but it looks like three לוג log of water. So do
you go by what it is in fact or do you go
by what it looks like? Okay, so this is the debate.
So it says שנפל למקוה, shenafal lemikvah, it fell into a מקוה,
mikvah, לא פסול, lo pasul, did not invalidate because you need it
to really be water. It doesn't matter what it looks like. Looks
don't matter, it matters what it is. רבי יוחנן בן נורי אומר,
Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri omer, רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben
Nuri says: הכל הולך אחר המראה, hakol holech achar hamareh, it all
goes by appearance. So if it looks like water, it has a
status of water even if it is, even if it's all water,
even if it's, even if it's not all water. Now by the
way, רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan Ben Nuri presumably would also
disagree in the following case. Let's say you had the case not
mentioned here. Well it all depends on the גירסא. girsa. But for
our גירסא girsa not mentioned here. Let's say you had three לוג
log of water and a little wine fell in. So what would
you have then? You would have the the full amount of water
but it looks like wine. So the rabbis who go by what
it actually is would say it invalidates a מקוה mikvah because it
actually is three לוג log of water, whatever it looks like it's
three לוג log of water. רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan Ben
Nuri presumably would stay his position whether to be strict or to
be lenient. I don't care what it is, I care what it
looks like. So even though it's three לוג log of water, now
it all looks like wine, it has a status of wine. So
what we are going to do is we are going to latch
on to רבי יוחנן בן נורי. Rabbi Yochanan Ben Nuri. Because רבי
יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan Ben Nuri basically says I define something's
identity more than just what's in front of me but in terms
of, you know, other character, more than what it like really is,
but in terms of other characteristics. So here's how we're going to
use רבי יוחנן בן נורי. Rabbi Yochanan Ben Nuri. So let's take
a look. Yes.
What if the minority of it was water and two thirds of
it was like milk, alcohol so it would be clear.
Right. And it looks like water. How far would רבי יוחנן בן
נורי Rabbi Yochanan Ben Nuri go? That's a good question because you
know there are other things that look clear. Why do I say
because it looks like water it's water? Maybe I should say it
looks like alcohol, it looks like milk, you know, if it's a
little bit cloudy. So that is a good question, you know, would
רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan Ben Nuri when he is,
you know, yeah, I don't, I don't know the full answer to
that. It might, it might at least minimally require that there's a
majority of what you're going to identify it as. So if you're
trying to identify it as water there has to at least be
a majority of water. That's, I just, you know, intuitively I would
say that's probably a minimum criteria of his but I'm not sure
it ever gets fully fleshed out. Okay. So let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara says לאו אמר רבי יוחנן בן נורי, Lav
amar Rabbi Yochanan Ben Nuri, does not רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi
Yochanan Ben Nuri say לאו אמר רבי יוחנן, Lav amar Rabbi Yochanan,
I'm sorry, בתר חזותא אזלינן? Batar chazuta azlinan? You define things based
on what they look like and regardless of what they actually are
although James of course raises an important question at some stage you
have to factor in what it actually is. But anyway a major
component is what they look like.
So הכא נמי זיל בתר חזותא וטעמא. Hacha nami zil batar chazuta
v'taama. Here too go by appearance and taste. So it's interesting of
course that it sticks in the word taste. We haven't seen that
yet but, but the גמרא Gemara is assuming that if appearance matters
taste should also matter. Now this is actually, I'll just sort of
say parenthetically, this is actually an important question because we know for
כשרות Kashrut issues the thing that matters the most is what something
tastes like. So for example, you know, if I have a tiny
little drop of חזיר chazir that falls into a soup, my soup,
and I want to know is my soup כשר kosher or not,
the question is can you detect the חזיר chazir taste? That's the
key question for food. Is the other food present is does it
have the taste? Here you know sometimes we're not always dealing with
food. If I want to know does a מקוה mikvah become invalid
or not and not asking my question about what, you know, do
I consider this to be what from a food perspective. Now if
I asked you how do we judge things' identities, you know, normally?
You know what's the basic way you see something you're going to
make a judgment what it is? So our primary sense is sight,
right? If something looks a certain way we assume it is something.
Our other senses like touch and taste or whatever are more secondary
to our way of, you know, of interpreting the world and making
judgments about what things are. But when it does come to food
issues taste is primary. So okay smell's also but that's secondary. But
when it comes to food that's a question also about does smell
matter by food and that's a whole discussion ריחא מילתא. Reicha milta.
Okay so when it comes to things' identity in the field of
כשרות Kashrut taste is the most significant and as Michael said smell
a little bit. When it comes to things' identity outside of the
field of כשרות Kashrut there the גמרא Gemara more emphasizes the appearance
and that's what רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan Ben Nuri was
talking about. Nevertheless here we have like an interesting intersection because if
I have to decide is this water winey water or whatever is
this תמד temed considered to be water or wine, it has relevance
for food issues like buying it with מעשר שני Maaser Sheni money
which is like a food issue, what type of a food is
it. It has relevance for non-food issues. Does it invalidate a מקוה
mikvah which is not a food question, it's just a general question
is it water or wine. So there's sort of both of those
you know both of those different factors at play. Now you could
have said we measure it differently for the different spheres but we've
been assuming we treat it the same across the sphere. So therefore
the גמרא Gemara feels comfortable throwing in the other criteria of taste
although רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan Ben Nuri only mentioned appearance.
So what the גמרא Gemara is saying is look we know רבי
יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan Ben Nuri is not only you know
says it's not only what the thing is it's the characteristics that
it that it sort of exhibits. So the same way he talks
about the characteristic of appearance also we should assume according to him
the characteristic of taste matters and that determines something's identity beyond what
it is. How's this all going to play in? So let's spell
it out. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: So לאו אמר
רבי יוחנן בן נורי בתר חזותא אזלינן lav amar Rabbi Yochanan ben
Nuri batar chazuta azlinan and he says you go by appearance, so
הכא נמי hacha nami here too זיל בתר חזותא וטעמא zil batar
chazuta v'taima go by appearance and taste. I've explained why the גמרא
Gemara felt comfortable throwing in taste. וחזותא דהאי מיא נינהו v'chazuta d'hai
maya ninhu and the appearance of this thing that is going to
ferment but has yet to ferment is that of water. So he
says like this: Remember our whole discussion is what is the status
of this watery wine, winey water that is going to ferment but
has not yet fermented? So we had a statement that oh if
it will ferment or as David says it's in the process of
fermenting it's already wine. But it doesn't yet taste like wine, it
hasn't yet fermented. So and our משנה Mishnah says that it's not
wine until it actually has fermented. So the גמרא Gemara says this
is the debate. If you ask me objectively what is this, this
is wine. It's something that's in the process of fermenting. But רבי
יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri doesn't just care what it
is objectively. רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri cares about
how does it appear, how does it taste, what type of characteristics
does it exhibit. And since it doesn't yet taste like wine and
doesn't yet appear like wine, for him he's not ready to call
it wine. So now that is how the גמרא Gemara has explained.
Our משנה Mishnah that demands that it actually ferments is רבי יוחנן
בן נורי. Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri. רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan
ben Nuri cares more about what is it actually exhibiting, and if
it's not exhibiting the appearance of wine or the taste of wine,
it's not wine. Whereas the statement of רבא בר אבוה Rava bar
Avuha that it says it is wine because it's in the process
of fermenting he says I don't care what it exhibits, I care
what it is, and something that's in the process of fermenting is
wine, even though it doesn't look or taste like wine yet it
is wine and that's the debate. So that's how the גמרא Gemara
tries to conceptualize the issue, is it what something is or is
it what something appears like. Where רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan
ben Nuri cares more what it appears like. Okay, so that's how
we resolve that part.
Yes, there's a little better language it's how do we experience it
versus what is its legal status.
Well no, both are debating what its legal status is.
Okay, as to how we experience it
as opposed to what it actually is.
Well, but actually is is
hard because actually is is based on a human categorization which is
often informed by how we experience it
as opposed to a standard that we cannot discern.
Right. Right. So I understand that is part of the whole problem
here is that in a case where it's water and milk, clearly
two very clearly different objects mixed up you could discuss what is
it really, what contents like what percentage water, what percentage milk, versus
how do we experience it and that is the debate of the
rabbis and רבי יוחנן בן נורי. Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri. In this
case about the water with the with the grape juice that's in
the process of fermenting,
it's not like it's X percent this and X percent that, the
whole question is at what stage do you define it as wine
and what stage not. So it's harder to apply their debate.
But רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri is saying why
does something that we experience as water be anything but water. Right.
Right. So to say what it really is, no, what my experience
is is what it really is.
Right. No I agree and that's and it's easier for him also
to say by this sort of, winey water is that it's also
still water because that's how we experience it. The harder thing is
to
explain what the rabbis are saying, they're saying even though you don't
yet experience it as wine since it's in that process and in
some objective way it's undergoing the same type of processes that wine
is
undergoing. Right.
So their argument is that if there's a something that is underway
and happening and could be measured by other factors that's not discernable
to a human
eye as it were.
Right, exactly. So it's but it's just that the rabbis what they're
measuring in the water-milk case is a little different than what they're
measuring in the water-grape juice case. In the water-milk case they're just
measuring ingredients, what ingredients are water, what ingredients are milk. In the
water-grape juice case they're measuring sort of what process is it undergoing
regardless of what we experience. But you're right, the common denominator for
רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri is how do we
experience it and because it's how we experience it, it's also the
point that I was mentioning that it's experience is maybe primarily through
its appearance but also through other senses as well, and the גמרא
Gemara feels comfortable introducing the issue of taste into that factor. Okay,
so yes, so that is how we explain the difference about we
now still experience it as water but it is can be judged
to be from another lens
something that is in a process of that of wine. Okay, ופליגא
u'pleiga so now the גמרא Gemara goes on, ופליגא דרבי אלעזר u'pleiga
d'Rabbi Elazar this argues on רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar is this way
of framing the debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and the rabbis,
remember them? About when you took out the same amount you put
in and we assumed that it was talking about that it had
fermented? That is against רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar דאמר רבי אלעזר d'amar
Rabbi Elazar because רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar says הכל מודים שאין מפרישין
עליו ממקום אחר אלא אם כן החמיץ. hakol modim she-ein mafrishin alav
mi-makom acher ela im ken hechmitz. Everybody, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and
the rabbis that debate this stuff when you took out the same
you put in, they would all agree that even the rabbis who
say as to even רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who says it's considered
to be wine, even he would say that you can't take תרומות
ומעשרות Terumot u'Maasrot with other wine
until it has fermented. So before we unpack that statement, what's important
for us If he says he assumes that ר' יהודה *Reb Yehuda*
and the Rabbis are debating when it hasn't fermented and he says
oh but you know even ר' יהודה *Reb Yehuda* that treats it
like wine he would not treat it fully like wine until it
has fermented. So for us the point is is that he is
saying that they're debating when it hasn't fermented, we were saying they
were debating when... he was saying that they're debating when it has
not yet fermented, we were saying that the debate was when it
had already fermented. Now let's understand this statement about why how he
what this issue is about taking תרומות *trumos* and מעשרות *maaseros* from
another place. קסבר *kasavar* he assumes בלא החמיץ מחלוקת *belo hichmis machlokes*
that ר' יהודה *Reb Yehuda* and the Rabbis are debating even when
it has not yet fermented which again makes the position of ר'
יהודה *Reb Yehuda* quite astounding. It hasn't fermented, you took out the
same amount you put in, how does he know that it's considered
to be wine yet? Okay so that's hard to understand but that's
their debate when it has not yet fermented. And here's what he
says: ועד כאן לא מחייב ר' יהודה אלא ela, מיניה וביה *ve'ad
kan lo mechayev Reb Yehuda ella minei u'vei*. So because ר' יהודה
*Reb Yehuda* is such a difficult position to understand, it hasn't fermented,
you haven't taken out more than you put in, so even ר'
יהודה *Reb Yehuda* that treats it as wine is only treating it
as wine like for its you know that you can take תרומות
*trumos* and מעשרות *maaseros* from the thing itself, meaning it's not really
fully wine yet. You know enough want to be מחמיר *machmir* and
maybe rabbinically treat it as wine and say take תרומות *trumos* and
מעשרות *maaseros* from it but it's not real wine. So he only
says you to take תרומות *trumos* and מעשרות *maaseros* מיניה וביה *minei
u'vei* from it on it. אבל מעלמא לא *aval me'almah lo* but
you can't take real wine and take from this watery stuff and
be מפריש *mafrish* you know and say that exempts me from taking
תרומות *trumos* and מעשרות *maaseros* from my real wine or from your
real wine take תרומות *trumos* and מעשרות *maaseros* and say that exempts
me from you know this watery stuff because this watery stuff because
it has yet to ferment is not real wine even according to
ר' יהודה *Reb Yehuda*. And what would be the problem if you
try to take תרומות *trumos* and מעשרות *maaseros* from this on real
wine or vice versa? דילמא אתי לאפרושי מן החיוב על הפטור מן
הפטור על החיוב *dilma ati la'aprushei min hachiyuv al haptur min haptur
al hachiyuv* because real wine is really obligated in תרומות *trumos* and
מעשרות *maaseros* and this watery stuff that has not yet fermented is
not really obligated, it's just like rabbinic or something. So therefore if
you take from real wine on it so well let's do the
first case first if you take from it on real wine you're
taking from something not obligated and exempting wine that's really obligated so
you haven't really taken תרומות *trumos* and מעשרות *maaseros* on your real
wine. That's obviously not good, מן הפטור על החיוב *min haptur al
hachiyuv*. But even מן החיוב על הפטור *min hachiyuv al haptur* is
not good because the way you compute how much you have to
take if I have five units of real wine and five units
of this water stuff so it's ten units I'm going to take
one unit of מעשר *maaser* right because that's one tenth of everything
but I really am only supposed to take a half a unit
of מעשר *maaser* because I really only have five units that are
really obligated. So the extra amount is not really is not really
מעשר *maaser* so I'm mixing everything up that I shouldn't be, I'm
doing all the proportions wrong and I can't do that as well.
So again the relevance is is that we've been assuming that ר'
יהודה *Reb Yehuda* says it's real wine and therefore we've been assuming
that the debate is at it's already fermented. Here's an approach to
say that no it's not yet fermented that's what they're debating but
so if that's true when ר' יהודה *Reb Yehuda* says it's obligated
it's not because it's real wine it's just some rabbinic thing and
you can't really treat it as real wine. Okay so with that
we end that issue but again our משנה mishnah *mishna* emphasizes the
issue of fermenting not how much you've put in and taken out
and the question is has it actually fermented or is it just
in the process of fermenting?
Can you use it as wine for the מקוה mikvah *mikva*?
ר' יהודה *Reb Yehuda* well according to this read presumably not because
this read it's only being מחמיר *machmir* and being strict but according
to...
is it treated as
water for the מקוה mikvah *mikva*? Presumably not, it's not clear. But
according to our read that he's talking that it has fermented then
yes then it's real wine
okay.
תנו רבנן *tanu rabbanan*: some were looking at it where was the...
I forget who said it but רבא *Rava* who said there was
a ר' יוחנן בן נורי *Reb Yochanan ben Nuri*. So therefore since
ר' יוחנן בן נורי *Reb Yochanan ben Nuri* goes by appearances or
experience and therefore since
it still feels like water and tastes like water it's water and
רבה בר בר חנה *Rabba bar bar Chana* whoever said בר אבוה
*bar Avuha* says no it's in the process of fermenting it's already
wine. Okay let's go on. תנו רבנן *tanu rabbanan*: התמד עד שלא
החמיץ *hatemed ad shelo hichmis* again this תמד temed *temed* which has
not yet fermented so it would be still water משיקו במים *mashiko
bemayim* you can put it in a מקוה mikvah *mikva* literally you
can kiss it to a מקוה mikvah *mikva*. You cannot kasher food,
you cannot purify... put food in a מקוה mikvah, *mikva* you know
you can only put in a מקוה mikvah *mikva* vessels, the Torah
only and not pottery vessels, the Torah only allows the מקוה mikvah
*mikva* to operate on vessels and on people not on food products
with the one exception of water. If your water became טמא tamei
*tamei* and you're the type of person that wants to even drink
your water when it's טהור tahor, *tahor* or you're a whatever the
case might be you can put your water into a מקוה mikvah
*mikva*. Now of course you know if you're not careful about it
it's going to get into all the dirty water and whatnot but
if you maybe do it in a very careful way and you
just touch it you know you lower the vessel in and you
just let the surface of the water to touch the water of
the מקוה mikvah. *mikva*. maybe you keep it relatively unsullied. Anyway, the
point is that because the מקוה mikvah. water and you're putting water
in a מקוה mikvah, it becomes like the מקוה mikvah water itself
and it becomes טהור, tahor, not because the מקוה mikvah purified it,
but because it became part of the מקוה mikvah water. So that
is a process that only works for water. So if your תמד
here became טמא tamei. and you want to make it טהור, tahor.
it depends if it's water or not. If it has yet to
ferment, it's still water, you can put it into the מקוה, mikvah,
kiss it to the מקוה mikvah water. How much water you're putting
in? No. The מקוה has to be full though, it has to
be forty סאה. se'ah.
Could you have forty-two סאה? se'ah?
Yeah, of course. Once your מקוה is forty סאה, se'ah, nothing you
add to it could be a problem.
Okay and it still makes your water טהור.
tahor Yeah, it's not a question here of majority, right. It's a
question of once it's defined as a כשר kosher מקוה. Okay. משהחמיץ,
mishehichmitz, once it has fermented, אין משקיקו במים, ein mashkiko bemayim, you
cannot kiss it to the water because it is no longer water,
it is wine. אמר רבא לא שנו אלא שתמדו במים טהורים ונטמאו.
amar Rava lo shanu ela shetimdo bemayim tehorim venitme'u. This is only
when originally the water was pure and then it became you added
the grape juice or whatever the leaves ונטמאו venitme'u and then it
became
טמא. tamei אבל טמאי מי קרא לא, aval temei mei ikara lo,
then you can certainly not kiss it to the water. Why not?
So it's not exactly clear, תוספות Tosafot explains because then it never
was just pure
then it changed, it became טמא tamei, as pure water and now
it's in this quasi water-wine state. So according to him, because it's
not, the גמרא's Gemara's going to reject it. But because it's not
in its original pure water state, you can no longer put it
in the מקוה. That's what he
says. So אתא רב גביה מבי כתיל אמרה לשמעתא קמיה דרב אשי.
ata Rav Gaviha mi-bei Katil amra lishmayta kamei de-Rav Ashi. And he
said it over to רב אשי. Rav Ashi. So רב אשי Rav
Ashi didn't understand it. He said, מאי שנא מטמאי מי קרא? mai
shna mi-temei mei ikara? Why, how is this different than something that
was originally טמא, tamei which you said you can not use it
in the מקוה, even if it has yet to ferment, דלא, delo,
that you're saying no, why? The only logic to that would be
דאמרינן איידי דמייא יקירי שחני תתאי ופירא קפי מעילא, de-amrinan idi de-maya
yakiri shachni tata'ei u-peira kafi mei-eila, because water is heavier, denser than
wine. Is that true? Does anybody ever try to mix water and
wine? Does the wine float on top? Okay. What? Is you think
it mixes equally? Maybe it depends on how dense. I imagine wine
is denser because it has the grape content in it. But anyway,
but this is just a little grape flavor. This assumes that the
water is denser. So it says שחני תתאי, shachni tata'ei, it dwells
at the bottom, it goes below, ופירא קפי מעילא, u-peira kafi mei-eila,
and the juice product floats on the top. So when you're touching
it to the מקוה water, right, the only thing that touches the
מקוה water is the surface of the water in your vessel, right,
you're taking your water in your vessel and putting it in. So
you're assuming that the problem with this mixture, even if it has
yet to ferment, is that only the juice is touching the water
of the מקוה and not the water itself. If that's true, ולא
סלקא לה השקה למיא, ve-lo salka lah hashkaka le-maya, and the kissing
doesn't work. So
אי הכי טהורים דסוף מיטמו נמי. ei hachi tehorim desof mitmu nami.
So if the exact same even if it became טמא tamei after
the juice was added. אלא, so how do you solve this problem?
מבלבלי, mevalbeli, you stir it up, you mix it before you put
it in the מקוה, so they haven't separated. הכא נמי מבלבלי, hacha
nami mevalbeli, here too you mix it up. So I don't understand
why it matters when it became טמא and that's how we conclude.
As תוספות Tosafot said that maybe it matters whether you consider the
same object or not, but that's rejected. So here's another application of
is it wine or is it water, can you put it in
the מקוה to make it טהור and interestingly the גמרא Gemara exploring
the physics of maybe given enough time the things will separate. So
with that we end. It's interesting the גמרא Gemara does not explore
the end of the משנה Mishnah, about what I think is a
fascinating concept. The one time you have this concept of corporation in
הלכה, halacha, the idea of inheriting an estate where it's considered to
be the sort of identity of the estate, not a partnership. But
the גמרא Gemara does not pay attention to that and we move
on now as I said, we're actually going through all of ש"ס.
Shas. So we've done קדשים, Kodashim, טהרות, Taharot, זרעים, Zera'im, a little
bit of נזיקין, Nezikin, I think with the brothers and the estate.
And now we're on to נשים. Nashim. We're going to do נשים
Nashim and מועד Moed
and with that make a סיום siyum on ש"ס Shas and with
that end the פרק. perek. So let's take a look. כל מקום
שיש מכר אין קנס וכל מקום שיש קנס אין מכר. kol makom
she-yesh mecher ein knas ve-chol makom she-yesh knas ein mecher. So where
there is sale, which means a father can sell his daughter into
slavery, which is when she is under age, less than twelve years
old, there is no קנס. knas. What's קנס? knas? The תורה Torah
says
if a man seduces or rapes a נערה, na'arah, a young woman,
then he pays a fine and in other types of consequences, fifty
כסף. kesef. So the תורה Torah says נערה. na'arah. נערה na'arah classically
understood by the Rabbis to mean a young girl who is technically
an adult, she's בת מצוה, bat mitzvah, twelve years old and two
pubic hairs, but she is not yet a full adult, which they
understand occurs six months later.
narrow period between 12 and a day and 12 and six months
and a day, which is when she is considered a נערה, na'arah,
a young woman. She's a woman already, but she's a young woman.
So that is where, that is where the fine of for somebody
who rapes her to seduce a woman comes when she's a נערה.
na'arah. So when there is מכר, mecher, when the father can sell
her, is when she's underage. When is there קנס, knas, when she
is a נערה. na'arah. So where there is sale, there is no
קנס. knas. Underage, there is sale but there is no קנס. knas.
Or there is קנס knas between 12 and a day and 12
and six months as a נערה, na'arah, then there is no sale
because she is not underage and the father cannot sell her.
It's like a free for all in other words? Anybody can rape
her
when she's underage?
Yeah. Well no, there are
other consequences other than קנס. knas. The consequences like, you know, what's
not explicit in the תורה, Torah, but what the rabbis say first
of all is that there's consequences of, you know, of like the
normal types of torts that would apply, you know, about damages and
so on, certainly in the case, you know, in the case of
rape and even in the case of seduction. The גמרא Gemara says
that פיתוי קטנה אונס, pitui ktanah ones, you know, which is basically
the concept of a statutory rape, that even if an underage girl
agrees to the act of sex, it's still considered force.
So Rashi says if she's raped, yeah, there's no קנס. knas. There's
no קנס. knas.
So that's what I'm saying. I'm saying that in addition to קנס,
knas, what the rabbis say, which isn't explicit in the תורה Torah
but they try to read it in, is that there are other
things that you pay like a person had, you know, had like
had beaten somebody, had done a, what's the word?
But it's not a big, it's not as great as...
I don't know, 50 כסף kesef is a certain amount. If somebody
is actually, if you're actually basically you're suing them for damages for
an act of rape, so that could be you talk about צער,
tza'ar, about right, pain and suffering. I mean, well, probably there's not
much in terms of ריפוי, ripui, but depends if not violent in
other ways, but it's pain and suffering, embarrassment, damages.
But if he seduced her...
But that's what I'm telling you, Rifka, פיתוי קטנה אונס. pitui ktanah
ones. Seduction of an underage girl is considered rape. Okay. The גמרא
Gemara has a concept of statutory rape. So anything that she is
a קטנה ktanah is number one considered rape even with her consent.
And if it's rape, there are serious consequences in terms of, you
know, in terms of personal damage. So there's not the קנס, knas,
but there is payments of personal damage, that there is.
Who is the beneficiary of the קנס? knas?
Oh, I was afraid you were going to ask that. I thought
I had managed to answer Rifka, but I was afraid of that
next question.
He
doesn't seem to know.
So even if she is a נערה, na'arah, the father does receive
the קנס. knas. But one minute, one of the reasons the father
receives the קנס knas is because the father, you know, right, is
this has to do with money that would have been given for
the כתובה, ktubah, which would have gone maybe, you know, to the
father. Well, that's okay, that's a whole other conversation. Anyway, yes, the
father receives the קנס knas and basically for the personal damages as
well, for the most part
it goes to the father too. For the personal damages it seems
like he's receiving the קנס knas
in respect to the damaged goods that he can no longer sell
at full price.
Oh yes, but not to put too fine a point on it.
Well, the גמרא Gemara says מכר, mecher, it's a sale.
Right, right, right, right. He's on the קנס knas case. David has
the floor.
Is he receiving the damages as a trustee or is he receiving
the damages also to his own account?
Yeah, that is a very good question and I have to, if
you give me one second I can double check. I'm pretty sure
for the most part it's to his own account, but I have
to double check.
בוגרת bogeret is older than נערה? na'arah? I'm sorry? בוגרת bogeret is
old enough anyhow? She doesn't get
the money
anyway.
It goes to her father, to her husband.
She never gets the money really, doesn't involve her.
Actually she does get the money. According to the גמרא, Gemara, she
does get the money if she's an adult, meaning by the time
when the when it goes to court. So according to the גמרא,
Gemara, there's times when the girl can get the money if, depending
on different opinions or whatever, if she's an adult when it actually
goes to court. But anyway, let me take a look at this.
So the רמב"ם Rambam says very explicitly here, I'll just read this
as response to you, Rifka. חמישים כסף של קנס הם דמי הנאת
שכיבה בלבד. chamishim kesef shel knas hem dmei hana'at shchivah bilvad. It's
only for the the 50 כסף kesef of the קנס knas is
for the pleasure that he illicit pleasure of the sex. Okay and
then he says
וחייב המפתה ליתן בושת ופגם יתר על הקנס. vechayav hamefateh litten boshet
upgam yeter al haknas. Okay and the seducer has to give embarrassment
and injury in addition to קנס. knas. יתר עליו האונס, yeter alav
ha'ones, the rapist, which would be any case of underage is considered
rape, שנותן את הצער, shenoten et hatza'ar, also pays for pain and
suffering. Okay and then the רמב"ם Rambam goes on.
But there's no קנס.
knas. I understand there's no קנס, knas, but there are damages. There's
pain and suffering and injury, right. So all so that's my first
point is that there's no קנס knas but there are all of
these personal injury. Now who receives it? Let me just double check
one minute.
But the
father
sells her and gets money for selling her and then she's abused,
he gets additional money. Just give me one second. Just give me
one more second. What would a woman
do with money anyway?
Thanks. That's the point. It's actually in the גמרא Gemara that women
didn't own money. Yeah, yeah, here you go.
שלושה דברים של מפתה וארבעה של אונס
הרי הן של אב שכל
שבח נעורים לאב ואם אין
לאב
הרי הן של עצמה.
Shlosha devarim shel mofateh ve-arba
shel ones harey hen shel
av she-kol shevach neurim la-av
ve-im ein la-av harey hen
shel
atzmah.
And then, however, if it goes to court after, when she's already
an adult, then she's entitled to it. So basically she has to
try to delay the court date until she's an adult.
But the father can then doubly profit. He gets the money when
he sells her. Right. And then if she's raped, the young girl
when
she's raped, he gets additional money.
Right, that is true.
That is true. That's true. So again, the only difference would be
if she was an adult when it went to court. Okay, so
let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רב יהודה אמר
רב זו דברי רבי מאיר. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav zu divrei
Rabbi Meir. Good thing we're not learning כתובות Ketubot right now so
we can get through this quickly. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב זו
דברי רבי מאיר. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav zu divrei Rabbi Meir.
This is the opinion of רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. וחכמים אומרים יש
קנס במקום מכר. Va-chachamim omrim yesh knas bimkom mecher. There is an
overlap. There's times where there's both a fine and sale, meaning they
understood that even when the girl is underage, there still is the
קנס, knas, that נערה na'arah does not mean, does not mean only
when she's a נערה, na'arah, it means when she's no older than
a נערה na'arah until she's up through being a נערה. na'arah. That
even as a minor, there's still the fine. דתניא, De-tanya, we taught
in the ברייתא, braita, קטנה, ketanah, a young girl,
מבת יום אחד עד שתביא שתי שערות, mi-bat yom echad ad she-tavi
shtei se'arot, until she has two pubic hairs, until she's בת מצוה
bat mitzvah and an adult and a נערה, na'arah, יש לה מכר
ואין לה קנס, yesh lah mecher ve-ein lah knas,
and there's no קנס knas in the case of rape or seduction
because she is, because she's not a נערה. na'arah. משתביא שתי שערות
עד שתבגר, Mi-she-tavi shtei se'arot ad she-tivager, from the time she has
two pubic hairs until she becomes, until she fully matures, which means
six months later, so now she is a נערה, na'arah, she's not
a minor, יש
לה קנס ואין לה מכר, yesh lah knas ve-ein lah mecher, and
she doesn't have sale. דברי רבי מאיר, Divrei Rabbi Meir, this is
רבי מאיר'ס Rabbi Meir's statement. שהיה רבי מאיר אומר, She-hayah Rabbi Meir
omer, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir used to say, and this is the
line of our משנה, mishnah כל מקום שיש מכר אין קנס וכל
מקום שיש קנס אין מכר. Kol makom she-yesh mecher ein knas ve-chol
makom she-yesh knas ein mecher. Where there's sale, there's not fine, where
there's fine, there's not sale, they're mutually exclusive periods, one is קטנה,
ketanah, one is נערה. na'arah. וחכמים אומרים, Va-chachamim omrim, but the sages
say, קטנה מבת שלוש שנים ויום אחד עד שתבגר יש לה קנס.
Ketanah mi-bat shalosh shanim ve-yom echad ad she-tivager yesh lah knas. No,
a woman is entitled to קנס, knas, or not she is, the
girl, thank you, and not she, the father, right, a baby, right,
there's קנס knas even for underage, but not starting at one day.
One day old is when the father can sell her, but קנס
knas is only when she's three years old, starts. Why? Because only
then is it considered to be an act of sex. Interesting, you
know, the rabbis say that when the girl is less than three
or the boy is less than nine, although the same physical things
happen, they don't consider it to be a הלכתי halachic act of
sex. So therefore it's only considered, it's only from the time she
is
three years old, thank you. קנס אין מכר לא? Knas in mecher
lo? What, you mean only קנס knas during that period? אימא אף
קנס במקום מכר. Eima af knas bimkom mecher. No, starting at three
years old, you have both. So basically the way it works for
the חכמים Chachamim is starting at one day old, the father can
sell her, okay, and from one day until three years,
all that happens is sale, there's no קנס. knas. From three years
till בת מצוה bat mitzvah is when both categories apply. The father
can sell her because she's underage and according to the rabbis there's
קנס knas because it's considered an act of sex and they don't
limit קנס knas to her being a נערה. na'arah. And then from
12 and a day to 12 and six months, there's only קנס.
knas. She's a נערה, na'arah, but she is not a minor, so
the father can't sell her. And from 12 years and six months,
then nothing. The father can't sell her, but there's also no קנס
knas because that's according to everybody. Okay, so those are those various
things. What?
There's no concept of child abuse in הלכה? halacha?
Yeah, that's always a problem when you deal with, right, and sell
her,
right, I know, but as abuse,
yes, it's
a very big problem but we don't have time to explore that
now. Okay, so we're going to try to finish up the פרק.
perek. כל מקום שיש מיאון אין חליצה וכל מקום שיש חליצה אין
מיאון. Kol makom she-yesh miun ein chalitzah ve-chol makom she-yesh chalitzah ein
miun. So here too is an issue within נשים, Nashim, within a
girl, at what stage can she do מיאון miun and חליצה. chalitzah.
So חליצה, chalitzah, as you know, is when she's married and her
husband dies. and there's no children and her brother either does יבום
yibum or does חליצה. chalitzah. Now there's a debate but this משנה
is assuming that חליצה chalitzah can only be done when both the
man doing the חליצה chalitzah and the woman to whom it is
done are adults. Okay, so חליצה chalitzah is only at the age
of adults, twelve years and a day. That's חליצה. chalitzah. What is
מיאון? miyun? מיאון miyun is when a girl is married off, as
we just got through saying, a father can sell his daughter. He
can also, as we know, marry off his daughter. Okay, what if
the father is dead? Then the girl when she's underage, nobody can
marry her off. But this really is interesting as it reflects the
societal reality of the need to sort of provide for daughters and
the need to marry them off, that the rabbis felt that there
was a need even when the father was dead to give the
power to the mother and the brothers to marry off the daughter.
So that again really speaks to a totally different society than we
are familiar with. So when the mother and the brothers marry off
the daughter, it is not yet halachically binding. It only becomes halachically
binding and the girl has the right at any time before she
becomes an adult to basically reject the marriage. Once, however, she becomes
an adult and she stays in the marriage, she can no longer
reject. So that period is called מיאון, miyun, rejecting the marriage. So
till when can she reject the marriage? Only while she's still a
minor, under twelve years and a day. So when there's מיאון, miyun,
there's no חליצה, chalitzah, because she's a minor; she can't do חליצה.
chalitzah. Meaning in different cases, one is a case she's married off,
the other is a case where she was genuinely married and the
husband died and blah blah blah. But we're not talking about, we're
talking about different cases. But the age of being a minor is
an age when מיאון miyun takes place and חליצה chalitzah cannot take
place. The age of being an adult is an age when there's
no מיאון miyun because she's already an adult, she can no longer
reject the marriage, but there is חליצה, chalitzah, a woman can do
חליצה chalitzah once she's an adult. So let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara.
Father marries off, she can't do...
Father marries off, there's no מיאון. miyun. מיאון miyun is only by
this rabbinic תקנה. takanah.
What, which category is נערה na'arah in terms of that?
Is not a נערה na'arah neither? Here it's, here it's from the
time... Oh no, I'm sorry, she is a נערה. na'arah. An adult
means a נערה, na'arah, she's already twelve years and a day. Okay,
אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, so Rav
Yehuda said in the name of Rav, זו דברי רבי מאיר, zo
divrei Rabbi Meir, this is the position of רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir,
אבל חכמים אומרים, aval Chachamim omrim, the sages say,
so again it's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who says these are mutually
exclusive, but the sages say יש מיאון במקום חליצה. yesh miyun bemakom
chalitzah. No, there's a stage when a girl can both do מיאון
miyun and חליצה. chalitzah. In this exact period when she's a נערה.
na'arah. When she's twelve years and a day, so she can do
חליצה, chalitzah, she's an adult, and she can even do מיאון, miyun,
even though she's already an adult and she stayed in the marriage,
she can still do מיאון. miyun. דתניא, detanya, we taught in the
ברייתא, beraita, עד מתי הבת ממאנת, ad matai habat mima'enet, till when
can a girl refuse this marriage of her mother and brothers? עד
שתביא שתי שערות דברי רבי מאיר, ad shetavi shtei se'arot divrei Rabbi
Meir, until she has two pubic hairs, which is what רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says, until she becomes an adult, a נערה. na'arah. רבי
יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, no, עד שירבה השחור על הלבן, ad
sheyirbeh hashachor al halavan, again
speaking a little euphemistically or not so euphemistically, whatever, until the black
increases on the white, meaning until there's a lot of pubic hair.
Actually, the גמרא Gemara reframes that to say it doesn't mean a
lot of pubic hair, just means that the pubic hairs are very
long. Okay, but regardless, basically it means that she has more time,
like presumably six months, the period of until she's a בוגרת. bogeret.
So he says there's a period when she's an adult and she
can do חליצה, chalitzah, twelve years and a day, and that she
can also still refuse this marriage of her mother and brothers, because
this whole marriage is rabbinic. Now, by the way, I wanted to
point out that there are two possibilities. What does it mean she
stayed in the marriage? One is she stayed in the marriage but
they haven't yet had sex, and the other is she stayed in
the marriage and after she was a twelve years and a day
they did have sex. In that case, even according to רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda she can't refuse, because if she is having sex with
this man as an adult, halachically an adult, I mean obviously for
us as Rivka says we'd call it child abuse, but halachically she's
called an adult, twelve years and a day, and having sex in
the context of marriage, then that becomes an act of marriage, that
becomes קידושי ביאה. kiddushei biah. Okay, but if she hasn't had sex,
then according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda she can still reject the
marriage until she becomes not only twelve years and a day but
up until she, you know, is a more fully an adult, until
she's let's say twelve years and six months.
She has six months to reject.
Six months more. Six months more. Everybody says you can reject it
as a minor. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you can even reject
it for the first six months that you're an adult.
But רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says she only has that one day.
No, not the one day. Up until she becomes an adult, her
entire time when she's a minor she can always reject.
But once she becomes the adult...
Then she can't reject it anymore. Immediate? Right, immediate. Okay, let's just
finish this up. Now we did נשים Nashim and now we're going
to do מועד. Moed. כל מקום שיש תקיעה אין הבדלה. Kol makom
sheyesh tkiyah ein havdalah. They would blow the שופר shofar ערב שבת
erev Shabbat to tell people to stop doing מלאכה. melachah. So when
you blow the שופר, shofar, you know, you do not make הבדלה.
havdalah. וכל מקום שיש הבדלה, vechol makom sheyesh havdalah, we might say
when you light candles you don't make הבדלה, havdalah, but they blew
the שופר, shofar, right? וכל מקום שיש הבדלה, vechol makom sheyesh havdalah,
when you're making הבדלה, havdalah, which is מוצאי שבת, motzei Shabbat, אין
תקיעה, ein tkiyah, you don't blow the שופר shofar because blowing the
שופר shofar is about forbidding מלאכה melachah and making הבדלה havdalah is
about allowing מלאכה. melachah. יום טוב שחל להיות בערב שבת, Yom Tov
shechal lihyot be'erev Shabbat, if יום טוב Yom Tov was on ערב
שבת, erev Shabbat, okay, so you're going to... from a period of
forbidden מלאכה *melachah* to more forbidden מלאכה *melachah*, תוקעין *tok'in*, you make,
you do blow, right, it's like we light candles, and you go
from יום טוב Yom Tov, *Yom tov* to שבת Shabbat *Shabbat*, same
sort of analogy, and לא מבדילין *lo mavdilin*, you don't make הבדלה
havdalla *havdalah*, and הבדלה *havdalah* is only when מלאכה *melachah* is being
made permitted. תוקעין *tok'in* is when מלאכה *melachah* is becoming forbidden. But
מוצאי שבת Shabbat *Motza'ei Shabbat*, if יום טוב *Yom tov* falls on
מוצאי שבת *Motza'ei Shabbat*, it's the opposite: מבדילין ולא תוקעין *mavdilin v'lo
tok'in*. You make, you do,
so then you make הבדלה *havdalah* because you're going from a heavier
prohibition to a lighter one, meaning, not necessarily heavier, but more things
are prohibited to fewer things are prohibited when you go from שבת
*Shabbos* to יום טוב *Yom tov*. We make הבדלה *havdalah* from שבת
*Shabbos* to יום טוב *Yom tov*, but you don't do תקיעה *teki'ah*
because it's because more things are not forbidden. Okay, so again, הבדלה
*havdalah* is when things are becoming permitted, תקיעה *teki'ah* is when things
are becoming forbidden. כיצד מבדילין *Keitzad mavdilin*, what ברכה *berakhah* do you
say in הבדלה *havdalah* from שבת *Shabbos* to יום טוב *Yom tov*?
'Cause you can't say המבדיל בין קודש לחול *hamavdil bein kodesh l'chol*,
it's not חול *chol*. So what ברכה *berakhah* do you say? So
you say, המבדיל בין קודש לקודש *hamavdil bein kodesh l'kodesh*. רב דוסא
אומר *Rav Dosa omer*, בין קודש חמור לקודש קל *bein kodesh chamur
l'kodesh kal*. You say between a heavy קדושה *kedushah* to a light
קדושה *kedushah*, so it's קודש לקודש *kodesh l'kodesh* but you explicate. Okay,
let's just finish up. היכי תוקע *Heikhi toke'a*? Let's see what time
it is. Do we have two minutes? Okay, well let's just do
this very quickly. היכי תוקע *Heikhi toke'a*? So how do you do
this תקיעה *teki'ah* when יום טוב *Yom tov* goes into שבת *Shabbat*?
How do you distinguish it from a standard תקיעה *teki'ah*? A standard
תקיעה *teki'ah* ערב שבת *erev Shabbat* would be a תקיעה *teki'ah* and
a תרועה *teru'ah*. Here it's יום טוב *Yom tov* going into שבת
*Shabbat*, it's a little different. How do you distinguish? So אמר רב
יהודה *amar Rav Yehuda*, תוקע ומביאה מתוך התקיעה *toke'a u'mevi'ah mitoch hateki'ah*.
Your תקיעה *teki'ah* turns into a תרועה *teru'ah*. It's not two separate
blows, but your תרועה *teru'ah* comes out of your תקיעה *teki'ah*, it
transforms into a תרועה *teru'ah*. רב אסי אומר *Rav Assi omer*, תוקע
ומביאה בנשימה אחת *toke'a u'mevi'ah b'neshimah achat*. You do it with one
breath, but you do it as two separate sounds, but you don't
take a big space between them. אתקין רב אסי בחוצל כשמעתיה *Itkin
Rav Assi b'Hutzal k'shmaiteh*. רב אסי *Rav Assi* established in חוצל *Hutzal*
to do like he had ruled, that the way you do it
from יום טוב *Yom tov* to שבת *Shabbos* is a תקיעה *teki'ah*
and a תרועה *teru'ah* within one breath. Okay, מיתיבי *meiteivei*, יום טוב
שחל להיות בערב שבת *Yom tov shechal lihyot b'erev Shabbat*, when יום
טוב *Yom tov* leads into שבת *Shabbos*, תוקעין ולא מריעין *tok'in v'lo
mari'in*. You do תקיעה *teki'ah* without תרועה *teru'ah*. מאי לאו *Mai lav*,
לא מריעין כלל *lo mari'in klal*? Doesn't it mean no תרועה *teru'ah*?
So he says, לא *lo*, no, רב יהודה מתרץ לטעמיה ורב אסי
מתרץ לטעמיה *Rav Yehuda metareitz l'taameh v'Rav Assi metareitz l'taameh*. Each one
will explain according to their position. רב יהודה מתרץ לטעמיה *Rav Yehuda
metareitz l'taameh*, here's how רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda* would explain it: לא
מריעין בפני עצמה *lo mari'in bifnei atzmah*. You don't do a separate
תרועה *teru'ah*, אלא מתוך התקיעה *ella mitoch hateki'ah*, but you do a
תרועה *teru'ah* that, you know, your תקיעה *teki'ah* transforms into a תרועה
*teru'ah*. You don't do a separate תרועה *teru'ah*. רב אסי מתרץ לטעמיה
*Rav Assi metareitz l'taameh*, רב אסי *Rav Assi* explains: לא מריעין בשתי
נשימות *lo mari'in b'shtei neshimot*. You don't do a תרועה *teru'ah* with
a big break between the תקיעה *teki'ah*, with two breaths, אלא בנשימה
אחת *ella b'neshimah achat*, you do them all in one breath. Fine.
That's how יום טוב *Yom tov* going into שבת *Shabbos*, the תקיעה
*teki'ah* which forbids מלאכה *melachah* is done slightly different because obviously מלאכה
*melachah* has already been forbidden, it's just now more מלאכה *melachah* is
being forbidden, so it's slightly different. Now let's get to הבדלה *havdalah*,
this is very interesting, this is about our practice. ובמוצאי שבת *U'v'motzei
Shabbat*, so this is so about saying המבדיל בין קודש לקודש *hamavdil
bein kodesh l'kodesh*, היכא אמר לה *heikha amar lah*? Where do you
say המבדיל בין קודש לקודש *hamavdil bein kodesh l'kodesh*, right? How do
you start הבדלה *havdalah*, right? You say, המבדיל בין קודש לחול, בין
ישראל לעמים, בין יום השביעי לששת ימי המעשה *hamavdil bein kodesh l'chol,
bein Yisrael l'amim, bein yom hashevi'i l'sheshet yemei hama'aseh*, right? So do
you say at the beginning המבדיל בין קודש לקודש *hamavdil bein kodesh
l'kodesh* or do you only say it at the end? So אמר
רב יהודה *amar Rav Yehuda*, בחתימתה *b'chatimatah*. No, you only say it
at the end. You start with בין קודש לחול *bein kodesh l'chol*,
you only in the ברכה *berakhah* you say המבדיל בין קודש לקודש
*hamavdil bein kodesh l'kodesh*, which is what we do. וכן אמר רב
נחמן *V'chein amar Rav Nachman*, בחתימתה *b'chatimatah*, in the end. רב ששת
בריה דרב אידי אמר *Rav Sheshet breih d'Rav Idi amar*, אף בפתיחתה
*af bifitichatah*. Even in the opening, you say המבדיל בין קודש לקודש
*hamavdil bein kodesh l'kodesh* and not בין קודש לחול *bein kodesh l'chol*.
ולית הלכתא כוותיה *V'leit hilkhata k'vathieh*. We don't rule like that. We
keep the, because as רש"י *Rashi* says, we keep the standard text
for that. We only, you know, and also the standard text reflects
biblical text. Because the תורה Torah. *Torah* says that God separated between
the holy, בין קודש לחול *bein kodesh l'chol*. The תורה *Torah* never
says God separated between קודש לקודש *kodesh l'kodesh*. So we want to
keep the biblical reference. Okay, just to finish this up. רב דוסא
אומר *Rav Dosa omer*, בין קודש חמור לקודש קל *bein kodesh chamur
l'kodesh kal*, between the heavy and the light. ולית הלכתא כוותיה *V'leit
hilkhata k'vathieh*. We don't rule like that. רש"י *Rashi* says it's not
respectful to call יום טוב *Yom tov* a light קדושה *kedushah*, so
we don't say that. אמר רב זירא *Amar Rav Zeira*, יום טוב
שחל להיות באמצע שבת *Yom tov shechal lihyot b'emtza Shabbat*. How about
when you just have a יום טוב *Yom tov* in the middle
of שבת *Shabbat*? What do you say in your הבדלה *havdalah*? Do
you say בין יום השביעי לששת ימי המעשה *bein yom hashevi'i l'sheshet
yemei hama'aseh*? Has it ever struck people a little bizarre when you
make הבדלה *havdalah* on יום טוב *Yom tov*, you say that God
separates between שבת *Shabbos* and the weekday 'cause it's not שבת *Shabbos*
and the weekday? So he says, nevertheless, that's what you say. אומר
המבדיל בין קודש לחול, בין אור לחושך *Omer hamavdil bein kodesh l'chol,
bein or l'choshech*, here's our נוסח nusach *nussach*, בין ישראל לעמים, ובין
יום השביעי לששת ימי המעשה *bein Yisrael l'amim, u'vein yom hashevi'i l'sheshet
yemei hama'aseh*. So you say between שבת *Shabbos* and חול *chol*, even
though it's יום טוב *Yom tov*, it's not שבת *Shabbos*. מאי טעמא
*Mai taama*? Why? סדר הבדלות havdallot הוא מונה *Seder havdalot hu moneh*.
Because you are just listing traditional הבדלות *havdalot*, and the way רש"י
*Rashi* says, all of these are in the תורה *Torah*. If you
just look at the last רש"י *Rashi*, he says they're all in
the תורה *Torah*. Such as סדר הבדלות האמורות בתורה *seder havdalot ha'amurot
b'Torah*, ויבדל בין האור ובין החושך *vayavdeil bein ha'or u'vein hachoshech*, right,
so that's המבדיל בין אור לחושך *hamavdil bein or l'choshech*, ואבדיל אתכם
מן העמים להיות לי *v'avdil etchem min ha'amim lihyot li*, that's בין
ישראל לעמים *bein Yisrael l'amim*, ובין יום השביעי *u'vein yom hashevi'i*. ששת
ימי המעשה so that's when it says in מעשה בראשית Ma'aseh Bereishit
that God separated off שבת and He sanctified it. So you have
all of these that we say in the הבדלה are הבדלות that
are mentioned in the תורה. So therefore we keep that נוסח even
when it's יום טוב, even when even when the שבת is not
immediately relevant. Okay.